# Amit Mukherjee (1) Featured

- \* Senior developer with 11+ years of experience in different Microsoft Technology stacks.
- \* Specialized working in cross-functional environment like support, development and testing.
- \* Has worked on Azure Data Factory, Azure Data Bricks, Azure Bot



Current Designation: Senior Associate Total Experience: 12 Year(s) 0 Month(s)

Current Company: Cognizant Technology Solutions India Ltd Notice Period: 2 Months

Current Location: Kolkata Highest Degree: B.Tech/B.E. [Computers]

Pref. Location: Delhi / NCR, Hyderabad, Kolkata

Functional Area: IT Software - Application Programming /

Maintenance

Role: Software Developer

Industry: IT-Software/Software Services

Marital Status: Single/unmarried

Key Skills: Senior Associate, Software Developer, Software Engineering, Design Development, SQL Server Integration Services, Project Management, Resource Management, Stakeholder Management, Requirement Gathering, Business

Intelligence, Web Technologies, Power BI

Verified: Phone Number | Email - id

Last Active: 21-Jan-21 Last Modified: 21-Jan-21

### Summary

- \* Senior developer with 11+ years of experience in different Microsoft Technology stacks.
- Specialized working in cross-functional environment like support, development and testing.
- \* Has excellent capability of collaboration, communication and reporting to senior stakeholders, customer service and resource management.
- \* Implemented Live Video Analytics on IoT Edge integrated with custom AI model to push data into IoT hub for power bi analysis.
- \* Has worked extensively on Power BI development and web page integration.

## **Work Experience**

# Cognizant Technology Solutions India Ltd as Senior Associate Dec 2013 to Till Date

\* Live Video Analytics on IoT Edge

Role: Azure IoT Developer and Azure Data Engineer (Jun 2020 - Present) Overview:

Designed and developed a product "Visual Decisions" sponsored by Cognizant for implementing social distancing at different retail stores keeping in mind the current COVID pandemic. The solution leverages an IoT Edge solution deployed on-premise to capture the live feed of the people densities located at different aisles in the stores at different points in time through IP surveillance cameras located at different points in the stores. The solution also leverages an on-premise ML model to detect the people count and the corresponding floor co-ordinates of the concerned people that are pushed to Azure Cloud for further processing and storage in CosmosDB. The data is then collected from Cosmos DB and displayed using Power BI to the end-users.

#### Roles and Responsibilities:

- \* Implemented the entire IoT Edge Solution end-to-end.
- \* Deployed Live Video Analytics module on IoT Edge.
- \* Developed and deployed custom AI modules on IoT Edge.

- Wrote Python code on Azure Data Bricks to capture live telemetry data from Event Hubs and push to Azure Cosmos DB.
- Developed heat maps using Power BI report for displaying the affected regions.
- Clean Energy For Everyone

Role: Azure IoT Developer and Azure Data Engineer (Dec 2019 - May 2020) Overview:

Designed and developed a product "Clean Energy For Everyone" sponsored by Cognizant for creating a prototype solution for detecting temperature and humidity baseline drifts to pro-actively alert the stakeholders to prevent any possible mishaps or accidents. This solution was presented in Cloud Hackathon 2020.

#### Roles and Responsibilities:

- Developed and deployed modules written in Python on Raspberry Pi device using Sensehat
- Raspberry BI acted as a transparent gateway between the sensors and Azure Cloud .
- Raspberry BI collected the readings from the sensors and pushed the live telemetry data to cloud.
- Created a Stream Analytics job to accept the live telemetry data from IoT hub to Power BI output.
- Created line charts using Power BI for plotting temperature and humidity in real time.
- Smart Assistant For a Leading Telecom Company Role: Azure Al Developer (Oct 2018 - Feb 2019)

#### Overview:

Designed and developed a smart assistant solution for a leading Telecom industry in Austria that helped to reduce the query response time for the end-users in case of network issues.

#### Roles and Responsibilities:

- Created a model in LUIS (Natural Language Processing Engine) for comprehending the intents and objectives of the end-users.
- Implemented Azure Search for quickly fetching records from Azure SQL database.
- Developed and deployed a chat bot in Azure
- Smart Assistant for a Leading Manufacturing Company

Role: Azure Al Developer (Oct 2018 - Feb 2019)

Overview:

Designed and developed a smart assistant solution for a leading manufacturing industry that helped the on-field technicians to quickly address the issues related to a pump.

#### Roles and Responsibilities:

- Created a model in LUIS (Natural Language Processing Engine) for comprehending the intents and objectives of the end-users.
- Developed a decision tree
- Developed and deployed a chat bot in Azure

# Nimbus Technology Solutions as Techno Functional Consultant

Feb 2011 to Nov 2013

#### Adapt Solutions Private Limited as Associate

Apr 2008 to Jan 2011

#### **Education**

UG: B.Tech/B.E. (Computers) from West Bengal University of Technology (WBUT) in 2007

#### IT Skills

Skill Name	Version Last Used Experience
Azure SQL, Power BI	
Microsoft Vision API	

Azure Data Bricks

\* Microsoft Business Intelligence Suite

# Languages Known

1/22/2021

Language	Proficiency	Read	Write	Speak
English				
Hindi				
Bengali				
French				

## **Affirmative Action**

## **Work Authorization**

Physically Challenged: No

Job Type: Permanent / Temporary

Employment Status: Full Time, Part Time